<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section title="Introduction" id="intro">

    <image src="frontpage.jpg" title="Grit Screenshot" caption="The 'playground' map." />

    The Grit Game Engine allows you to create rich 3D interactive worlds using Lua scripting.  All gameplay logic,
    graphical elements, physical behaviour, AI, sound, and everything else is ultimately controlled via general-purpose
    Lua APIs.  This manual serves as a reference for the APIs and frameworks for those APIs, complete with discussion
    and examples.

    <section title="Licensing" id="intro_licensing">

        Grit is open source and is released under a liberal license.  It can be used for both commercial and
        non-commercial projects.  The copyright and license for the code and assets within the project package breaks
        down as follows:

        <section title="Core Works" id="intro_core">

            Grit core works consist of:

            <ul>
                <li> The C++ code for the engine itself. </li>
                <li> Python and Maxscript code used in exporters. </li>
                <li> All Luaimg code. </li>
                <li> All assets and Lua code in system/. </li>
                <li> All Lua code in common/ and vehicles/. </li>
            </ul>

            These works are sufficient to build a game containing custom assets.  It covers all non-trivial code
            released as part of Grit.  The works are relased under the MIT license:

            <pre>
                Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a copy
                of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"), to deal
                in the Software without restriction, including without limitation the rights
                to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense, and/or sell
                copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the Software is
                furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

                The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included in
                all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

                THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EXPRESS OR
                IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY,
                FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
                AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER
                LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM,
                OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN
                THE SOFTWARE.
            </pre>

        </section>

        <section title="Example Content" id="intro_example">

            There is also some example content provided with the engine, and
            the copyright situation for these is more complex.  It is not
            expected that third parties will be re-using and reselling these
            assets, as they exist only to demonstrate the engine.  Furthermore,
            unlike source code, it is hard to find good quality assets under
            permissive licenses.

            Some assets have copyright owned by project contributors, and are
            released under liberal licenses such as MIT or CC-BY, just like the
            source code. But other assets have less liberal licenses such as
            CC-SA, CC-NC or GPL.  Furthermore, many assets are taken from stock
            image sites and thus copyright is still owned by those sites.  In
            these latter cases, care must be taken to use the assets in
            accordance with the appropriate licenses, as dictated by their
            copyright owners.

            Each directory has a copyright.txt file that lists the copyright
            owner, license of each asset in that directory.  Each element of an
            atlas will be described in copyright.txt unless all elements of the
            atlas are subject to the same license.  Modifications to assets may
            also be mentioned in copyright.txt. Any important restrictions on
            the license are also given.

        </section>

    </section>

</section>
