<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section title="Miscellaneous" id="misc" splitbelow="true">

    <section title="Lua" id="lua">

        Lua is a general purpose scripting language. It is well-known for
        having a small and fast implementation but a wide set of features
        including co-operative threading (co-routines), closures, self-style
        object orientation, and so on. Lua is more expressive and faster than
        all of the mainstream scripting languages and is used in many computer
        games.

        It is used extensively for scripting objects and for defining maps and
        so on. A little knowledge of Lua can go a very long way whether you are
        a programmer, artist, or even user of Grit.

        To learn Lua quickly, read chapter 2 of <web
        url="http://www.lua.org/manual/5.2/">its manual</web>.

        Lua is used in Grit with some minor modifications that make Lua
        code written for Grit incompatible with a regular Lua interpreter
        and regular Lua programs potentially incompatible with Grit.

        It should be possible to make regular Lua code work in Grit with
        minor (probably zero) modifications and the same performance. It is
        very unlikely that Grit Lua code will work outside of the
        customized Grit Lua VM without running much more slowly.

        <section title="Unicode" id="lua_unicode">

            All Lua files are now UTF-8. The string class in Lua has been
            rewritten to properly understand unicode. E.g. #"£" is 1, not
            2. The most visible difference is that the syntax for regular
            expressions has changed. The new syntax is that of <web
            url="http://userguide.icu-project.org/strings/regexp">ICU's
            regular expression engine</web>. For documentation, see
            sections "Regular Expression Metacharacters", "Regular
            Expression Operators" and "Replacement Text".

        </section>

        <section title="Vectors &amp; Quaternions" id="lua_vectors">

            Grit Lua scripts are often used to transform and manipulate objects
            in screen space and 3D space, as well as to manipulate colours.
            This is easiest with primitive vector (2d, 3d, 4d) and quaternion
            values.  For performance reasons, we cannot use userdata or tables
            for our vector and quaternion values.  This puts too much pressure
            on the garbage collector.  Thus, the VM has been modified so that
            vector2,3,4, and quat are primitive types just like 'number',
            'boolean' and 'nil'. They are copied by value and are not garbage
            collected.  The following code shows some of the ways they can be
            used:

            <lua>
                Q_ID = quat(1, 0, 0, 0)      -- constructing quaternions and 3d vectors
                V_ID = vec(0, 0, 0)
                V_NORTH = vec(0, 1, 0)
                V_EAST  = vec(1, 0, 0)

                local v = vec(1, 2, 3)
                print(v)
                print(v + v)
                print(2 * v)
                print(v * 2)
                print(v / 2)
                print(v * v)                   -- pointwise multiplication
                print(dot(v, v))               -- dot product
                print(norm(v))                 -- normalise
                print(cross(V_NORTH, V_EAST))  -- cross product
                print(-v)                      -- opposite direction, same length

                print(Q_ID)

                print(Q_ID * v2)               -- transform a vector

                local q2 = quat(180, vector3(0, 0, 1))  -- angle/axis form
                print(q2)
                print(q2 * v2)  -- transform a vector by a quaternion

                local q3 = Q_ID * q2 -- concatenate quaternion transformations
                print(q3)
                print(q3 * v2)
                print(inv(q3) * q3 * v2)  -- invert a quaternion

                print(v2 == v2)  -- equality is pointwise on the elements
                print(q2 == q2)
                print(q2 ~= q3)

                print(#v2) -- length (pythagoras)
                print(#q2) -- length (should be 1 for quaternions used to represent rotations)

                print(unpack(v2)) -- explode into x, y, z
                print(unpack(q2)) -- explode into w, x, y, z

                print(quat(90, vector3(0,0,1)) * (V_NORTH + V_EAST)) -- angle/axis constructor form
                print(quat(V_NORTH, V_EAST))                         -- quat between two direction vectors
                print(quat(V_NORTH, V_EAST) * V_NORTH)

                print(V_NORTH.yx) -- arbitrary swizzling is supported
            </lua>

        </section>

        <section title="Not A Number (NaN)" id="lua_nan">

            If you divide by zero in regular lua, you get a NaN value that goes
            on to pollute other code, making debugging difficult. In Grit we
            instead trap the divide by zero with an error instead of returning
            NaN.

        </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Mathematics" id="maths">

        <section title="Quaternion Basics" id="maths_quaternion">

            Quaternions are used to represent rotations in 3d space. They may seem scary, especially if you read <web
            url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quaternions_and_spatial_rotation">wikipedia articles</web> on the subject.
            The maths behind them is advanced, but you don't need to understand that in order to use them in Grit.

            Quaternions are just a clockwise rotation of a given number of degrees about a given axis (think like
            screwing in a screw). Part of the reason they seem scary is that they are often given in 'raw' form like so:

            <lua>
                quat(1,0,0,0)
            </lua>

            These 4 floating point numbers are the in-memory representation of the rotation.  They are labeled
            <def>w</def>, <def>x</def>, <def>y</def>, <def>z</def>, in that order.  The fact that only 4 numbers are
            needed is the reason quaternions are popular.  The most reasonable alternative, rotation matrixes, require 9
            numbers.  This particular quaternion is very important, as it is the <def>identity quaternion</def>.  It
            represents a rotation of 0 degrees.  When writing Lua code you can use the <def>Q_ID</def> global variable
            to make this more explicit.

            It is possible to understand raw quaternions if you are reasonably good at mathematics, but it is much
            clearer to give quaternions in their angle/axis form. Here is the same quaternion in angle/axis form (you
            can choose any axis, since it is 0 degrees of rotation).  These quaternion values all test equal:

            <lua>
                quat(0, vec(0,0,1)) == Q_ID
                quat(0, vec(1,0,0)) == Q_ID
            </lua>

            A rotation of 0 degrees about any axis is not very useful. The following is a more interesting quaternion:

            <lua>
                quat(90, vec(1,0,0))
            </lua>

            This means a clockwise rotation of 90 degrees about the 'X' axis.  To visualise this, imagine screwing a
            screw in the direction of the X axis. If you turn the screw 90 degrees, what used to point in the direction
            of the Y axis now points towards the Z axis. Likewise, what used to point in -Z now points towards Y.

            To specify an anti-clockwise rotation about the X axis, one can invert either the angle or the axis.
            Inverting both results in an identical quaternion.  The following are all equal:

            <lua>
                quat(-90, vec(1,0,0))
                quat(90, vec(-1,0,0))
                quat(0.7071068, -0.7071068, 0, 0)
            </lua>

            Generally, if you see a quaternion with 0.7 in the first value, it is a rotation by 90 degrees, whereas 0
            indicates 180 degrees.  In both cases, the last 3 numbers taken as a vector3 give the axis of rotation.
            Here are some example of 180 degree rotations:

            <lua>
                quat(0, 1, 0, 0) -- 180 degrees about X
                quat(0, 0, 1, 0) -- 180 degrees about Y
                quat(0, 0, 0, 1) -- 180 degrees about Z
            </lua>

            Note that there are many different ways of rotating by 180 degrees.  E.g. a barrel roll, turning on the
            spot, and doing a backflip. You can in fact rotate by 180 degrees about any axis and the result is different
            in each case.  On the other hand if you rotate by 0 degrees than it does not matter which axis you rotate
            around, because you are not rotating at all.

            You can also get the quaternion that would transform one vector into another: The following quaternions all
            specify a rotation of 90 degrees about the 'X' axis.  In the first case Y is turned to Z, and in the second
            case -Z is turned to X.

            <lua>
                quat(vec(0,1,0), vec(0,0,1))
                quat(vec(0,0,-1), vec(0,1,0))
            </lua>

            It is possible to see the raw form of a quaternion by typing these other forms into the console.  Also, one
            can easily extract the axis and angle from a quaternion using <def>q.axis</def> and <def>q.angle</def>.

        </section>
            
        <section title="Representing Orientations" id="maths_orientation">

            The difference between a rotation and an orientation is that a rotation is a change in orientation. It is
            like the difference between an absolute value and an offset. In order to use an offset as an absolute value,
            we must assume a base value from which to offset to the value we want. In the case of simple numbers and
            positions, it is clear that the base value should be 0, or vec(0,0,0) respectively. However with rotations,
            one uses the identity quaternion, or quat(1,0,0,0) as a base.

            For models, no rotation at all just means that XYZ in model space point in the same directions as XYZ in
            world space.  However for lights, an unrotated light will shine in the +Y direction. Thus if you want it to
            shine in the -Z direction then it needs to be rotated by the following quaternion:

            <lua>
                quat(vec(0,1,0), vec(0,0,-1))
            </lua>

            Having lights shine in +Y by default is an arbitrary decision.  Other applications instead prefer +Z, -Z,
            etc., so one must be careful when converting lighting setups from other software into Grit.

        </section>

        <section title="Transforming Vectors With Quaternions" id="maths_transform">

            If you have a point (or a direction, in the form of a direction vector) in model space, and you want to
            transform it into world space, you use the orientation of the object to rotate that vector.  For example if
            you want to know if a car is upside down, you can trotate the up vector for the car in model space,
            vec(0,0,1), by the car's orientation, and test if it is still pointing up.

            <lua>
                (car_orientation * vec(0,0,1)).z > 0
            </lua>

            This operation can be chained.  If you have a turret on a tank, and the turret usually faces +Y in model
            space, but you want to know where it points in world space given the turret angle (clockwise from the top)
            and tank orientation, you could use:

            <lua>
                turret_point_model_space = quat(turret_angle, vec(0,0,-1)) * vec(0,1,0)
                turret_point_world_space = tank_orientation * turret_point_model_space
            </lua>

            You can also combine the two quaternions into a single one that describes the complete rotation:

            <lua>
                turret_orientation_world_space = tank_orientation * quat(turret_angle, vec(0,0,-1))
                turret_vector_world_space = turret_orientation_world_space * vec(0,1,0)
            </lua>

            You can also invert a quaternion, which simply is the opposite rotation, i.e. the opposite angle around the
            same axis:

            <lua>
                inv(quat(35, vec(0,1,0))) == quat(-35, vec(0,1,0))
            </lua>

            This allows you to find out e.g. where the turret should point at in model space, in order for it point in a
            particular direction in world space.  From there you can e.g.  use math.atan2 to figure out the angle for
            the turret.

            <lua> 
                turret_point_model_space = inv(turret_orientation_world_space) * vector_to_enemy
            </lua>

        </section>

    </section>

</section>

