<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section title="The Heads Up Display (HUD)" id="gfx_hud">

    The <def>heads up display</def> (HUD) is a 2D framework for providing a
    graphical user interface to the player.  Like everything else, it can be
    extensively customised via Lua.  The most basic API allows positioning and
    rotating text / textured rectangles in a scenegraph-like hierarchy on the
    screen.  On top of this, various widgets have been implemented in Lua, via
    <def>HUD Class</def> definitions.  This, you are also free to make your
    own.  The HUD subsystem is designed to handle things like health/ammo
    displays, mini-maps, menu screens, and general purpose mouse-driven
    graphical user interfaces.

    <section title="Basics" id="gfx_hud_basics">

        Let us first instantiate an existing class.  The <def>Rect</def>
        HUD class is the simplest class it is possible to write, as it has
        no user-defined behaviours.  Its one-line definition is in the
        common/hud directory, but you can also define your own.
        Instantiate it as follows:

        <image src="hud_example1.png" title="Basic HUD object example">
            Use of /common/hud/Rect as shown in the Lua snippet.
        </image>

        <lua>
            obj = gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Rect`)
            obj.position = vec(100, 100)  -- centre of object, from screen bottom left
            obj.texture = `/common/hud/textures/Icon064.jpg`
            obj.size = vec(50, 50)
            obj.colour = vec(0, 1, 1)  -- cyan (masks texture)
            obj.zOrder = 2
            obj.alpha = 0.5
            obj.orientation = 44  -- degrees (clockwise)
            ...
            obj:destroy()
            -- Can also initialise members with a table param:
            obj = gfx_hud_object_add(`Rect`, {size=vec(50,50), ...})
        </lua>

        The HUD object has a number of fields that define how it is
        rendered.  Some examples of these are above, and they are
        comprehensively documented <todo>here</todo>.  If not given, they fall
        back to defaults first in the HUD class and then the system defaults.

        The size defaults to the size of the texture, if one is given.  The
        zOrder field is an integer between 0 and 7, which defaults to 3.
        Higher values are drawn on top of lower values.  The HUD object is
        garbage collected when it is abandoned, and can be destroyed earlier
        with :destroy().

        Rect can be useful for simple things but usually we will define our own
        <def>HUD class</def>, which has fields and methods much like a game
        class.  The HUD class can be instantiated into as many <def>HUD
        objects</def> as we want.  The following HUD class implements a
        spinning icon:

        <lua>
            hud_class `SpinningIcon` {
                texture = `/common/hud/textures/Icon064.jpg`,
                speed = 20,
                init = function (self)
                    self.needsFrameCallbacks = true
                    self.angle = 0
                end,
                destroy = function (self)
                    -- nothing to do
                end,
                frameCallback = function(self, elapsed)
                    self.angle = (self.angle + elapsed*self.speed) % 360
                    self.orientation = self.angle
                end,
            }
        </lua>

        <image src="hud_example2.png" title="Spinning Icon">
            The icon on the right (faster_obj) spins faster than the one on the left (obj).
        </image>

        The 3 defined methods are all callbacks, and there are other possible
        callbacks as well.  You can also define your own methods with your own
        names, to help structure your code or to provide a public API to the
        object.  The init callback sets the angle field of the object and
        requests frame callbacks.  If you enable a callback, you had better
        have a method of the right name to receive it.  If a callback raises an
        error, the system will usually disable the callback by setting the
        needsX field to false again.

        Note how giving the speed in the class allows it, optionally, to be
        overridden on a per-object basis.  The following code shows how we can
        override the speed when we instantiate the object:

        <lua>
            obj = gfx_hud_object_add(`SpinningIcon`, {position=vec(200,100)})
            faster_obj = gfx_hud_object_add(`SpinningIcon`, {position=vec(300,100), speed=30})
        </lua>

    </section>

    <section title="Corner Mapped Textures" id="gfx_hud_corner">

        By default, when a texture is set on a HUD object, it is filtered
        (stretched or shrunk) to fit the rectangular size of the object.  This
        can be useful when the size of the object can vary at run time, or if a
        single texture is to be used for a variety of differently sized HUD
        objects.  However, the filtering artefacts can look ugly for a lot of
        textures, especially when the texture is magnified a lot.
        
        <image src="hud_example7.png" title="Corner Mapped Texture">
            The texture itself is shown to the right.  To the left is shown the
            HUD object mapping this texture with corner mapping.
        </image>

        For certain kinds of textures, there is a technique that avoids the
        artefacts while allowing arbitrary scaling of the HUD object.  This
        involves mapping the four quarters of the texture 1:1 into the corners
        of the HUD object and stretching a single row and column of texels
        across the middle of the HUD object.

        This works well in a variety of situations where the centre of the HUD
        object is a solid colour, but detail is desired around the edge and at
        the corners.  For example, simple rounded corner rectangles, borders,
        bevels, etc.  Some example textures are provided in
        /common/hud/CornerTextures.  See the <sref
        id="gfx_hud_button">button</sref> class below for a concrete example.

        <lua>
            o = gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Rect`, {texture=`MyTexture.jpg`})
            o.size = vec(100, 100) -- larger than the texture
            o.cornered = true -- enable corner mapping
        </lua>

    </section>

    <section title="Text" id="gfx_hud_text">

        HUD text bodies allow the rendering of text according to a particular
        <sref id="gfx_font">font</sref>.  It supports top/bottom colour, ANSI
        terminal colour codes, hard tabs, new lines, wrapping according to a
        pixel width, and scrolling.

        <image src="hud_example3.png" title="Basic Text Rendering">
            A HUD text body using the simple misc.fixed font.
        </image>

        The text bodies behave like HUD objects, but they are not extensible.
        They do not have customisable fields and methods, and they cannot
        receive callbacks.  They do, however, have all the basic fields of
        HUD objects.

        <lua>
            t = gfx_hud_text_add(`/common/fonts/misc.fixed`)
            t.text = "Hello World!"
            t.position = vec(300, 300)
            t.orientation = 90
            t.zOrder = 7
            ...
            t:destroy()
        </lua>

        The size field of text is immutable.  Upon setting the text, it gives
        you the number of pixels occupied by this particular text in this font.
        The code takes account of tabs, new lines, and ANSI terminal colour
        codes.  

        <section title="Text Colour" id="gfx_hud_text_colour">

            Colour and alpha are supported via two mechanisms.  Firstly, and most
            simply, one can set the colour/alpha fields, which act as a general
            mask on the colour/alpha present in the texture.  This is the same as
            regular HUD objects.
            
            <image src="hud_example4.png" title="Per-Letter Colouring">
                Text with per-letter colouring.
            </image>

            To apply colour and alpha to individual letters and words, and to use
            top/bottom colouring (gradients) there is a different mechanism.
            Instead of setting the text field, one uses several calls to append(),
            between which the letter colour/alpha can be changed.  The clear() call
            will reset the state.  Setting the text field is equivalent to calling
            clear(), setting the colours to white and the alphas to 1, and then
            calling append().

            <lua>
                t:clear()
                t.letterTopColour = vec(1, 1, 0) -- yellow
                t.letterBottomColour = vec(1, 0, 0) -- red
                t.letterTopAlpha = 0.7
                t:append("Some firey text\n")
                t.letterTopAlpha = 1
                t.letterTopColour = vec(.5, .5, 1)
                t.letterBottomColour = vec(.5, .5, 1)
                t:append("and some pale blue text.")
            </lua>

        </section>

        <section title="Text Drop Shadows" id="gfx_hud_text_shad">

            <image src="hud_example5.png" title="Drop Shadows">
                A drop shadow of 1 pixel towards the bottom right of the screen.
            </image>

            To allow clearer reading of the text on arbitrary backgrounds, it is
            possible to enable a drop shadow.  This works by rendering the text
            first coloured black, at an offset, and then rendering the actual text
            in a second draw on top of it.  In the second case below, the texel
            lookup are offset by 0.5 texels, which causes bilinear filtering.  This
            has the same effect as blurring the text with a 2x2 box filter.  Note
            that there must be an additional pixel of space around each letter in
            the font texture for this to work.

            <lua>
                t.shadow = vec(1, -1) -- bottom right by 1 pixel
                t.shadow = vec(1.5, -1.5) -- pixel blurring
            </lua>

        </section>

        <section title="Wrapping Paragraphs" id="gfx_hud_text_wrap">

            By default, the text body will only break the text at any
            new-line characters (`\n`) given in the input text.  This means the
            width of the text body will be the length of its longest line.
            To automatically wrap the text at a given width in pixels, set the
            textWrap field, which defaults to nil.

            <lua>
                t.textWrap = vec(500, 400)
            </lua>

            This defines a rectangle.  Firstly, text is broken to avoid it
            rendering wider than the given number of pixels (500 in this case).
            Secondly, no more lines are drawn than would fit into the given
            height (400 pixels in this case).  The size field will always
            return the textWrap dimensions when it is non-nil, regardless of
            how much text is in the text body.  Lines are broken at word
            boundaries unless a word is too long for the line.

            It is also possible to scroll the text, i.e. to clip lines at the
            top of the text, as well as, or instead of, the bottom of the text.
            This is done by setting the scroll field, which defaults to 0.

            <lua> t.scroll = 200 </lua>
            
            This starts rendering at 200 pixels below the top of the given
            text, i.e. represents a scrolling down of 200 pixels.

        </section>

    </section>
    
    <section title="The Hierarchy" id="gfx_hud_tree">
    
        Like the 3D scene, the HUD objects exist in a hierarchy, i.e. one can
        be the child of another.  This is achieved by setting the parent field:

        <image src="hud_example6.png" title="The Hierarchy">
            The child is drawn relative to the parent.
        </image>

        <lua>
            p = gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Rect`, {
                colour = vec(1, 0, 0),
                position = vec(400, 150),
                size = vec(40, 40),
            })
            c = gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Rect`, {
                alpha = 0.5,
                position = vec(10, 10),
                size = vec(15, 15),
            })
            c.parent = p
            p.orientation = 45
        </lua>

        The object p has a child object c.  This relationship was established
        by setting its parent field, which can be changed at any time or
        provided in the constructor's 2nd argument.  HUD objects can be
        children or parents, but HUD texts can only be children.  A tree is
        thus formed, with HUD objects at the nodes, and either HUD objects or
        HUD text at the leaves.

        The position of the child is relative to its parent and is always drawn
        on top of the parent.  In this case it displays in the parent's upper
        right corner.  Setting <code>zOrder</code> is only necessary to
        disambiguate the draw order of siblings, as it is never possible to draw
        a parent on top of a child.  Disabling a parent causes all children to
        effectively be disabled as well.

        Typically, this hierarchy is used to implement more high-level GUI
        elements in terms of low-level ones.  For example, a GUI dialog might
        consist of buttons and text entry widgets.  Disabling the dialog would
        hide everything, and the dialog can be moved / rotated as a single
        atomic unit.
        
        As the parent's position (or orientation) is updated, the child's
        derived position and orientation are recalculated.  It is also possible
        to set <code>inheritOrientation</code> to <code>false</code>, which is useful to
        avoid icons rotating within a spinning mini-map, or to keep text looking
        crisp and clear (rotated text can be slightly blurred).

        Note that the child will be garbage collected if there is no link to it,
        so it is standard to store a link from the parent to the child in order
        to keep it alive.  The 'parent' field itself is a <def>weak</def> link,
        in that it does not in itself prevent the parent from being garbage
        collected.  However usually the parent is accessible from somewhere else
        (perhaps another parent or some top level variable).

        When a HUD object is destroyed, its children are automatically
        destroyed with it.  If you don't want this behaviour, you can unlink
        the children in the destroy callback by setting their parent to nil.

        <section title="The parentResizedCallback" id="gfxhud_tree_callback">

            Finally, children can react to parent resize events.  This is useful
            to build "responsive" dialogs that re-arrange their contents upon
            resize.  For example, a HUD object that is supposed to fill its
            parent can resize itself when the parent resizes.

            This is achieved by setting <code>needsParentResizedCallbacks</code>
            to <code>true</code> and then defining a method called
            <code>parentResizedCallbacks</code> that (other than
                    <code>self</code>) has a single parameter giving the parent
            size as a vector2.

            <lua>
                hud_class `Expanding` {
                    init = function (self)
                        self.needsParentResizedCallbacks = true
                    end,
                    destroy = function (self)
                        -- nothing to do
                    end,
                    parentResizedCallback = function(self, psize)
                        self.size = psize
                    end,
                }
            </lua>

        </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Handling Keyboard/Mouse Input" id="gfx_hud_input">

        Handling keyboard/mouse input allows us to create interactive HUD
        objects, for example buttons, text entry, scroll bars, etc.  There are
        two callbacks that provide this fundamental capability -- one for mouse
        pointer movements, and one for button events (both mouse and keyboard
        buttons).  They are both enabled by setting needsInputCallbacks:

        <lua>
            hud_class `InputDemo` {
                init = function (self)
                    self.needsInputCallbacks = true
                    self.inside = false
                end,
                destroy = function (self)
                    -- nothing to do
                end,
                mouseMoveCallback = function(self, local, screen, inside)
                    print(local, screen, inside)
                    self.inside = inside
                end,
                buttonCallback = function(self, event)
                    if inside then
                        print(event)
                    end
                end,
            }
        </lua>

        The mouseMoveCallback gets the cursor position local to the object
        (with derived orientation and position transformations reversed), the
        screen cursor position, and a boolean indicating whether the mouse
        cursor is over the HUD object or not.  This takes into account other
        HUD objects that may be occluding this HUD object.  If inside is true,
        then the local position should be within the rectangle defined by the
        HUD object's size.

        The buttonCallback receives all keyboard and mouse button events
        whenever needsInputCallbacks is true.  So typically, you should
        implement some code to implement mouse or click focus in order to
        disregard button presses when they should not be processed.  Grit does
        not prescribe a focus strategy, but it is trivial to implement one, as
        shown in the above code.

        The received events are strings.  Each string consists of a prefix
        character, one of +, -, =, or :, that denotes the action.  For example
        +a means a was pressed, -a means a was released, and =a is a repeat
        event, issued by the operating system because the key is being held
        down.  For such keys, the suffix of the key is the name of the button,
        which is always lower case.  Buttons like the arrow keys have names
        that begin with an upper case letter, e.g. "Left" or "Ctrl".  The mouse
        buttons have names beginning with a lower case letter, such as "left",
        "middle", and "right".

        Key events beginning with the ":" character are text events.  These
        incorporate the shift key for capitalisation, internationalisation
        accent keys, and other keyboard modifiers that affect the way text is
        typed.  So use these events for text input, do not try and capitalise
        letters yourself by watching for the shift key.

    </section>
    
    <section title="Existing HUD Classes" id="gfx_hud_existing">

        In /common/hud there are a few existing classes you can use to build
        GUIs quickly.  /common/hud/Rect is an example, and we have already seen
        several example applications in <sref id="gfx_hud">this chapter</sref>.
        The other classes are more sophisticated.  In all cases, the code for
        these classes is available to be read.  This is useful to find out how
        to instantiate them, and also to see examples of HUD code, for those
        writing their own HUD classes.  Some key classes are documented here:

        <section title="Button" id="gfx_hud_button">

            The class /common/hud/Button can be used to create a clickable
            button with text on it.  The button changes colour on mouse hover
            and click, and can also be greyed out.  It can be instantiated as
            follows.  Note the pressedCallback, which the code in this class
            executes when it receives a button press.  

            <image src="hud_example8.png" title="Button">
                The button created by the Lua snippet left.
            </image>

            <lua>
                b = gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Button`, {
                    caption = "Click Me!",
                    pressedCallback = function (self)
                        print("You clicked me!")
                    end,
                })
                -- By default, size is chosen based on the caption size.
                b.parent = my_dialog
                b.position = vec(40, 0) -- position within the parent
                b:setGreyed(true) -- turn the button off, default false
                b.enabled = false -- hide the button, default true
            </lua>

            It is also possible to customize some of the attributes of the
            button.  The following rather garish button demonstrates this.

            <image src="hud_example9.png" title="Garish Button">
                The colours become more interesting upon mouse interaction.
            </image>

            <lua>
                b = gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Button`, {
                    size = vec(100, 40),
                    font = `/common/fonts/Impact24`,
                    caption = "Click Me!",
                    baseColour = vec(0, 0, 0),  -- Black
                    hoverColour = vec(1, 0, 0),  -- Red
                    clickColour = vec(1, 1, 0),  -- Yellow
                    borderColour = vec(1, 1, 1),  -- White
                    captionColour = vec(1, 1, 1),
                    captionColourGreyed = vec(0.5, 0.5, 0.5),  -- Grey
                })
            </lua>

        </section>

        <section title="Label" id="gfx_hud_label">

            The /common/hud/Label class encapsulates a HUD text body.  It
            provides a simple way of aligning the text, and has the ability to
            set the text to grey, which is useful when greying out a whole
            dialog, including text labels.

            <lua>
                label = gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Label`, {
                    size = vec(100, 40),
                    alignment = "LEFT",  -- Also, "CENTRE", or "RIGHT".
                    value = "Enter number of things here: ",
                    position = vec(30, 30),
                    greyed = true,
                })
                label:setValue("Changed value: ")
                label:setGreyed(false)
            </lua>

        </section>

        <section title="Border" id="gfx_hud_border">

            The /common/hud/Border class wraps a child object and draws a
            border around it using <sref id="gfx_hud_corner">corner
            mapping</sref>.  When instantiating the class, the child object is
            given and automatically has its parent set to the border object.

            <image src="hud_example10.png" title="Border">
                Putting a border around another HUD object.
            </image>

            <lua>
                o = gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Border`, {
                    position = vec(200, 200),
                    padding = 8,  -- Extra space on the inside.
                    colour = 0.25 * vec(1, 1, 1),  -- Dark grey
                    texture = "/common/hud/CornerTextures/Border04.png",
                    -- The child object:
                    child = gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Button`, {
                        caption = "Some button.",
                    })
                })
            </lua>

            <todo> Editbox, scale, controls </todo>

        </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Layout" id="gfx_hud_existing_layout">

        By making use of the HUD hierarchy, one can position HUD objects
        using relative co-ordinates.  When creating a dialog, this means
        hardcoding the positions of all the elements of that dialog, which
        can be tedious and hard to maintain.  There are a few HUD objects
        that control the layout of their children, making this easier.

        <section title="StackX and StackY" id="gfx_hud_stacks">

            The /common/hud/StackX and StackY HUD classes will control the
            positions of their child objects and arrange them into horizontal
            or vertical alignment.  StackY will place the children vertically,
            in order, starting from the top.  StackX does the same but
            horizontally, starting from the left.
            
            Ultimately, the size of the stack object will be the bound of all
            the objects inside it, allowing you to nest stacks, add borders,
            etc.  The stack cannot be directly resized, it also does not react
            to children whose size change at some time after the stack was
            created.

            <image src="hud_example12.png" title="Border">
                Three buttons laid out using StackY.  Note the extra gap of 10
                pixels.
            </image>

            <lua>

                o = gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/StackY`, {
                    position = vec(200, 200),
                    padding = 8,  -- Default space between elements (defaults to 0)

                    -- The child objects:
                    { align="LEFT" },  -- "RIGHT" and "CENTRE" (default) also available.
                    gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Button`, {
                        caption = "Shoot Missile.",
                    }),
                    gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Button`, {
                        caption = "Shoot Laser.",
                    }),
                    vec(0, 10),  -- It's also possible to add extra space (or subtract it).
                    gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Button`, {
                        caption = "Place Mine.",
                    }),
                })

            </lua>

            Each element in the list is either the next child object, a vector2
            value giving some padding (which behaves like an invisible Rect of
            the same size), or a string that specifies a new alignment.  The
            alignment applies to all subsequent objects, unless it is changed
            again.

            The StackX is the same, except obviously they are placed one after
            each other from left to right.  Also, the alignment options are
            "TOP", "CENTRE", and "BOTTOM", and any additional spacing is given
            as vec(0, n) instead of vec(0, n).

        </section>

        <section title="Stretcher" id="gfx_hud_stretcher">

            The /common/hud/Stretcher class will position its child object to
            fill the given space.  It does this by changing its own position
            (the child is at vec(0, 0) relative), and size, and also changing
            the child's size to fill its own boundaries.  If the child has an
            updateChildrenSize callback, it calls that after changing the child
            size.

            The class is instantiated by overriding the calcRect function,
            which allows the user to specify how the size of the stretcher
            should relate to its parent's size.  The callback is re-executed
            every time the parent size changes.  The result of calcRect is
            passed to setRect, i.e. it is the values left, bottom, right, top.
            In this case, it specifies a 50 pixel padding, and the Stretcher
            has no parent, so it uses the screen dimensions as input.

            <image src="hud_example11.png" title="Stretcher">
                Using the /common/hud/Stretcher class to resize a button to
                fill the screen.
            </image>

            <lua>
                o = gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Stretcher`, {
                    calcRect = function(self, psize)
                        return 50, 50, psize.x-50, psize.y-50
                    end,
                    child = gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Button`, {
                        caption = "Some button.",
                    })  
                })  
            </lua>

        </section>

        <section title="Positioner" id="gfx_hud_positioner">

            The /common/hud/Positioner controls its own position according to
            the size of its parent.  It is typically used to place other
            objects relative to the four corners of the screen, and update
            these positions as the resolution or window size changes.  There
            are 5 existing positioner objects you can attach a HUD object to
            (by setting them as parent):  hud_center, hud_bottom_left,
            hud_bottom_right, hud_top_left, and hud_top_right.

            <lua>
                o = gfx_hud_object_add(`/common/hud/Rect`, {
                    size = vec(100, 100),
                    parent = hud_top_left,
                    position = vec(50, -50),
                })
            </lua>

        </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Bringing it all together" id="gfx_hud_summary">

        <todo>Some sort of complete example.</todo>

    </section>

</section>
