<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section title="Resources" id="resources">

    Resources are things like <code>/foo/bar/MyThing</code>, that are named using a path from the
    base game directory.  They may or may not actually exist as files on disk.  Typically resources
    either represent assets defined in Lua files, such as classes, objects, materials, etc. (covered
    in the various other chapters of this book).  Or, they represent assets on disk, such as sound
    files, textures, meshes, etc.  The latter, <def>disk resources</def>, are the subject of this
    chapter.

    <section title="Disk Resource Management" id="disk_resource_management">

        Disk resources can either be loaded or unloaded, which means whether or not they are
        occupying RAM (this can be CPU RAM or GPU RAM).  Loading usually takes a noticeable amount
        of time, so it's a bad idea to do it during gameplay.  When a body is created that depends
        on a resource, e.g. a GfxBody depending on mesh and texture resources, those resources will
        be automatically loaded (if needed).  However, loading the resource immediately before
        creating the body will introduce a noticeable delay.
        
        In a streaming game, the objects declare their required resources (usually in the class) and
        these resources are loaded in a background thread.  The object is not activated until the
        resources are available.  In this situation you rarely have to worry about loading /
        unloading resources.  However in a non-streaming game it can be simpler to load everything
        before gameplay begins.
        
        There are a number of API calls that can be used to manually control the loading and
        unloading of resources.  In the following calls, <code>name</code> is an absolute path.  To
        give a relative path, use backticks <sref id="lua_paths"/>.

        <lua>
            disk_resource_load(name)  -- Note: Raises an error if it's already loaded
            disk_resource_ensure_loaded(name)  -- Load, or no-op if already loaded
            disk_resource_loaded(name)  -- Test if loaded
            disk_resource_reload(name)  -- Useful during development to see new assets
        </lua>

        Using the above calls, it is possible to load resources way ahead of time.  This is useful
        in a game that is not large enough to need streaming, as you can load everything before the
        actual gameplay begins, or switch out resources between levels.  However there is a catch;
        Grit manages the available memory and GPU memory.  If, upon load, there is not enough CPU or
        GPU RAM, Grit will unload the least recently used resource(s) to make space for the one
        being loaded.  A resource is used if it has at least one user:
        
        <lua> disk_resource_users(name)  -- How many users does a resource have?  </lua>

        If you use a resource in some explicit way (e.g. create a GfxBody that uses a mesh), then
        Grit will automatically ensure it is not unloaded by increasing the user counter for that
        resource.  However, if you want to prevent unloading during a time when the resource is not
        actually used, you need to tell Grit that you're really still using it.  To tell Grit that
        you're using a resource, you create and keep a <def>hold</def> on it:

        <lua>
            myhold = disk_resource_hold_make(name)
            -- Resource will not be unloaded by Grit but may not be loaded yet
            disk_resource_ensure_loaded(myhold.name)  -- Load only if unloaded
            myhold:destroy()
            -- Now Grit may unload it if there is a RAM shortage
            -- Or you can force the unload now:
            disk_resource_unload(name)  -- Works only if users == 0
        </lua>

        Note that creating a hold on an object does not load it, but it will stop it being unloaded
        by the system until the hold is released.  Loading a resource when you don't have a hold on
        it can be dangerous because Grit may unload it again, causing a stall when you next use it.
        The idiom is therefore always to create the hold, then load the resource, keeping the hold
        until you don't need to use the resource anymore.

    </section>

    <section title="Disk Resource System" id="disk_resource_system">

        The following calls allow you to query the state of the system itself:

        <lua>
            disk_resource_num()  // Count all disk resources.
            disk_resource_num_loaded()  // Count all loaded disk resources.
            disk_resource_all()  // List all disk resources.
            disk_resource_all_loaded()  // List all loaded disk resources.
            host_ram_available()  // CPU RAM cap (configured by user).
            host_ram_used()
            gfx_gpu_ram_available()  // GPU RAM cap (configured by user.
            gfx_gpu_ram_used()
        </lua>

        The following flag helps debug stalls during rendering.  It enables a warning if resources
        are loaded in the foreground thread.  In non-streaming games, you can turn this on after
        loading your level to ensure that you loaded everything ahead of time.  In between levels,
        you can disable it, do your unloading/loading work and then re-enable it.  In streaming
        games, you can leave it on while the game is streaming to ensure you haven't forgotten to
        declare resources used by your objects.

        <lua>
            option("FOREGROUND_WARNINGS", true)  -- Enable warnings if resources are loaded too late
        </lua>

    </section>

</section>
